<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning | Marcos M. Raimundo</title>
    <link>mraimundo/tag/machine-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="mraimundo/tag/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Machine Learning</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>mraimundo/media/icon_huda5467b54b3ac186660d9d90f6e309e1_14712_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Machine Learning</title>
      <link>mraimundo/tag/machine-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fair and Transparent Credit Scoring</title>
      <link>mraimundo/projects/credit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>mraimundo/projects/credit/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethical AI</title>
      <link>mraimundo/projects/ethicalai/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>mraimundo/projects/ethicalai/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiobjective optimization in machine learning</title>
      <link>mraimundo/projects/mol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>mraimundo/projects/mol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Machine learning problems commonly have to deal with implicit or explicit conflicting objectives, thus leading to trade-offs. One of the most traditional is the model complexity vs. error rate on training trade-off. However, more complex is the model, more capable to adapt to data, thus reducing error; and vice-versa. But there are many other conflicting goals such as: error rate on each class; error rate vs. interpretability; error rate vs. fairness metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous research investigated the impact of optimization methods in machine learning, finding interesting impacts of multi-objective optimization in model selection, ensemble diversity, and knowledge sharing for classification problems, and esulted in applications in biology, medicine, logistics, and power transmissions; and also have theoretical contributions to machine learning, operations research, and multi-objective optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has three main goals: 1) Create a software framework to ease modeling and running conflicting objectives in machine learning; 2) Investigate theoretical consequences of modeling machine learning problems as multi-objective ones; 3) Creation of models to be employed in a wide sprectrum of applications. As a result, we expect to create a helpful framework that would machine learning experts to model tasks with conflicting objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
